In the last video,
we defined escalations and
their benefits and went
over when to execute them.
In this video, we're
going to cover how
to communicate change
to your project team.
You've probably come to
an understanding that
effective communication leads to
positive outcomes in every
aspect of your life.
The same is true for communicating
changes in projects.
Communicating change to
project team members
and stakeholders
isn't just a matter of
keeping your tracking
documents up to date.
Even the smallest changes
will be meaningful to
someone on your team and
should be communicated.
It's also true that
you'll need to tailor
your communication
tactics based on
the subject matter and recipient.
As a project manager,
sometimes you're
going to want to have
a meeting with your whole team,
while other times an
email might suffice.
Personally, I prefer having
a quick coffee or
hallway chat with
my teammates and then
following up with
an email, noting what
we agreed upon.
This is particularly
useful when you need
quick agreement or if the
subject is a little sensitive.
How will you know
which communication
tactic is appropriate?
Ultimately, you'll have
to use your own judgment,
but here are some ways you can
decide which route to take.
As a project manager,
when communicating a small change
that will affect an individual,
it's a good idea
to send an email.
Be sure to avoid emotional topics
or anything that needs to
be discussed in depth.
Just give them a heads up
and set a meeting time.
Weekly meetings may
not be necessary,
particularly if your
agenda is short.
If you set a meeting and
then decide against it,
you can either pivot
to an email or
move the topic to
a different forum.
When there's a big change
within your project that impacts
more than one person and is
likely to change the budget,
deadline, or scope
of the project,
you'll probably want to
have a team meeting.
One useful tactic to keep
in mind when navigating
these changes in your
project is called a timeout.
A timeout means taking a moment
away from the project in
order to take a breath,
regroup, and adjust
the game plan.
A timeout may temporarily
disrupt your momentum,
but it may be
absolutely necessary to
set you up for success
in the long run.
You may want to take a
timeout when the client
wants to redefine the
scope of the project
or if team members
get reassigned to
other projects and you need
a plan to backfill them.
This timeout is a chance
for the project team to
evaluate the changes so they can
adjust the plan as needed.
Throughout the process,
you will want to hold
meetings in order to
discuss successes,
setbacks, and possible future
improvements to the project.
These meetings are
called retrospectives.
Retrospectives are held
throughout the
project's life cycle.
A retrospective focuses on
identifying the
contributing causes of
an incident or pattern of
incidents without
blaming one individual.
While conducting a retrospective,
you should always assume
that everyone has
good intentions and did
the right thing with the
information they had,
whether or not it worked
out well in the end.
There's always a chance
to learn and do better.
As a project manager,
it's important to identify
effective techniques
for communicating
changes to an individual
teammate or to your whole team.
You now know a bit
more about taking
a timeout and the idea
of a retrospective
to have productive conversations
about incidents that arise
during your project,
and we will discuss this more
towards the end of the course.
All of these things will help
you on your journey to become
a successful project
manager. Let's keep going.